(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-08-21T14:24:30.945099",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
思い通りにいかないことだらけ
So many things don't go the way I want,
どうしようもなく自己嫌悪
with hopeless self-loathing.
八百万の痛みや悲しみから
From countless pains and sorrows,
逃げ込める場所を探してる
I'm searching for a place to escape.
いっそ岩の間に引きこもって
I might as well hide away in a rocky crevice
月も太陽も無視して眠ろう
and sleep, ignoring the moon and sun.
生まれてきたことの意味なんて
The meaning of being born into this world,
知らない 分かんないよ
I don't know, I don't understand.
でも そんな風に思えるってこと
But the fact that you can feel that way
それは 君がもっともっと素敵になれる
tells me you have the power
力があるって教えてるんだよ
to become even more wonderful.
そうさ 神のまにまに 仰せのまにまに
That's right, as God wills, as the heavens will,
誰だって地球を愛している
everyone loves the Earth.
飲めや歌えや どんちゅう騒ぎ
Drink, sing, and make a ruckus,
たまにはそんなのもいいね
that's nice once in a while.
そうさ 北も南も 右も左も
That's right, north and south, right and left,
なんだかんだ地球を愛している
we all love the Earth in our own way.
泥んこだけど歩いて行ける
We're muddy, but we can keep walking,
まだまだ先は長いさ
and we still have a long way to go.
ただ正しい人でいたいだけ
I just want to be a righteous person,
きっと誰もがそう願っているけど
I'm sure everyone wishes for that, but...
八百万の心の醜さに苦しめられる毎日さ
every day we're tormented by the ugliness of millions of hearts.
奇跡と言えば聞こえはいいけど
Calling it a miracle sounds nice, but
それはきっと偶然にすぎなくて やっぱ意味なんてないさ
it's surely just a coincidence, with no real meaning after all.
でも 例えば君にいじわるをするやつがいるなら
But if there's someone being mean to you...
思い通りにいかないことだらけ
With so many things not going my way,
どうしようもなく自己嫌悪
I feel hopelessly self-loathing,
八百万の痛みや悲しみから
from countless pains and sorrows,
逃げ込める場所を探している
I'm searching for a place to escape.
そうさ 神のまにまに 仰せのままに
That's right, just go with the flow, as gods say,
誰だって地球を愛してる
everyone loves the earth!
僕が笑って君も笑えば
When I smile up at you and you smile too,
許せないことなんてないよ
then we know that it's all been forgiven.
そうさ 北も南も右も左も
That's right, north and south, right and left,
なんだかんだ地球は回ってる
we all love the earth in our own way.
泥んこだけど歩いて行ける まだまだ先は長いさ
Even if we're muddy, we can keep walking, we've still got a long way to go!
本当に大事なものはなんて
All those things that you'd never expect
安っぽいくだらないことの中に あるよ
are hidden among seemingly pointless things.
時にはみんなで馬鹿騒ぎ 花を咲かそう
So let's all have fun and make a scene, let's make flowers bloom,
大きな花まで届くくらいの
a flower big enough to reach the sky!
そうさ 神のまにまに 仰せのままに
That's right, just go with the flow, as gods say,
もっともっと自分を愛せるよ
you can learn to love yourself even more!
鏡を見てごらんよもう分かるでしょ
Take a look in this mirror, don't you see now?
みんなを照らす光さ
You're the light that illuminates everyone!
そうさ 神のまにまに みんなありがとう
That's right, just as gods say, thank you everyone!
やっぱり地球を愛してる
I really do love the earth after all!
花を咲かそう 大きな花を 天まで届くくらいの
Let's make flowers bloom, big flowers, ones that reach all the way to heaven!
ラララ…
La la la...
ということで、100万人記念配信始まりました！
And so, the 1 million subscriber celebration stream has begun!
イェーイ！
Yay!
おめでとう！おめでとう！おめでとう！
Congratulations! Congratulations! Congratulations!
ときちゃん、いや今日はね、本当に素敵な大切な仲間のみんなが、お祝いに駆けつけてくれて、
Sora-chan, today I am so truly happy that all our wonderful and precious friends rushed over to celebrate,
本当に本当に嬉しく思っています。みんなありがとねー！
thank you so much, everyone!
おめでとうございます！ありがとうございます！
Congratulations! Thank you so much!
見てきてくれてみんなもありがとう！というわけで、早速みんなを紹介したいと思いますよ！
Thank you everyone for watching too! Now, without further ado, I'd like to introduce everyone!
はーい！に志衛からの刺客もとい、天乃少女白上だよ！
Hi! I'm Shirakami, the girl from the mountains, also acting as an assassin from NishiE!
今日はそらちゃんが今まで頑張ってきた集大成の日ということで、駆けつけました！みんなで盛り上げてお祝いしていくぞ！
Today is the culmination of everything Sora-chan has worked hard for, so I rushed over! Let's get hyped up and celebrate together!
イェーイ！おめでとう！
Yay! Congratulations!
そして、はい！起立、気をつけて、こんにちは！に志衛といえばちょっとじゃくはいもの気もしますが、月のミトをお見舞いします！よろしくお願いいたします！
And next, yes! Stand up, attention, hello! Speaking of NishiE, I feel a bit like a rookie, but I'll pay my respects to Tsukino Mito! Nice to meet you!
ミト様100万人おめでとう！
Mito-sama, congratulations on 1 million!
おめでとう！おめでとう！おめでとう！おめでとう！駆けつけてくれてありがとう！
Congratulations! Thank you for rushing over!
そらちゃん、本当に100万人おめでとう！
Sora-chan, huge congratulations on 1 million!
皆さん、フェチお姉です！よろしくお願いします！おめでとう！
Everyone, it's Fetish Onee-san! Nice to meet you! Congratulations!
おめでとう！
Congratulations!
そして、えーに志衛のすらのも起立気をつけ！あれあれあれ？
And, um, NishiE's Sura also stands up and pays attention! Huh, huh, huh?
まぶだちゆーれー！よろしくお願いします！
Bestie ghost! Nice to meet you!
あれ、みとちゃん、あれ、ゆにちゃんってもしや...
Wait, Mito-chan, wait, Yuni-chan, could it be...
そうですよね。
That's right.
私、こう言う場では後輩になることが多かったんですけど、今回、今やですね、私よりも後輩が...
I usually ended up being the junior in these kinds of settings, but this time, now, I have juniors even more junior than me...
いいね！可愛いね！
That's great! So cute!
ただ、一学年下ではあるかもしれないけれども、なんだか突然どうしてそうなったの！？
Still, even though you might be one year below, why did things suddenly turn out like this?!
今日ね、そらちゃんとこのすごい上下関係のあるメンツが集まったから、今日ね！
Today, since this group with a strict hierarchical relationship gathered together, today!
ギスギスしてる？ギスギス...
Is it tense? Tense...
いや、急に100万人配信なので、ギスギスやりますか？そらちゃん...
No, since it's a 1 million subscriber stream so suddenly, should we do a tense bit? Sora-chan...
仲良くね。まあそういうの言いつつ、
"Get along well," we say,
私たちはもうかなりもう長くやっている方で、
but we've actually been doing this for quite a long time.
そうだな。そうだな。
That's right. That's right.
このメンバーで集まるのってすら久しぶり。
It's been so long since this group gathered like this.
いや、本当だよね。
Yeah, seriously.
私、ちゃんとそらちゃんと会うのいつ？
When was the last time I actually met Sora?
2年ぐらい？
Like, two years ago?
この中で1年以内に会った人いないですよ、私。
None of us have met each other within the past year.
いや、いない。いない。
Yeah, true. True.
いや、いないですね。
Yeah, none of us have.
あっ、待って。
Wait, hold on.
さっちゃんのこと見て。さっちゃんの前ですよ。
Look at Sacchan. We're right in front of Sacchan!
よりね、よりやらなきゃ。もっともっとね。
We gotta try harder. Much, much more.
あ、でも私言ってた。
Ah, but I was saying—
みんなと1年以内に会った、あ、会った、会った、会ったよね？
We've all met within the last year, right? Right?
会った、会った、会った。
We have, we have!
最初だけじゃない？今だけだよ。
Isn't it just at the start? Only right now.
今だけだよ。もっと仲悪くなるかも。
Only right now. We might get on worse later!
いやいや、そんなことない、今だけだよ。
No, no way, that's not true, only right now.
仲悪くなるかも、でも大丈夫だよね。
We might drift apart, but it'll be fine.
今日でね、仲を深めていきましょう。ねっ、ねっ、ねっ。
Let's deepen our friendship today! Right, right, right?
というわけで、今日のハッシュタグなんですけど、
So, for today's hashtag,
「ときのそら100万人への奇跡」というハッシュタグになっておりますので、
it is "#TokinoSoraMiracleTo1Million",
ぜひぜひみなさん、
so everyone, please—
みなさん、
everyone—!
どうしよう。違う違う違う、なんか、え、背筋が寒くなって。
What should I do? No, no, no, somehow, uh, my spine is getting cold.
いや、なんか、「背筋が寒くなってくる」って言われてるけど、寒くなってはいないです。
No, like, people are saying "your spine is getting cold," but it's not actually cold.
ええと、そこでね、じゃあ、友利ちゃんとみとちゃんと仲良く慣れんのかな、とか、
Umm, so, like, wondering if I can get along well with Tomori-chan and Mito-chan,
そういうね、とか、そういう、手遅れじゃないですか。
or stuff like that—wait, isn't it already too late?
手遅れだけ。そういうのをね、もう年々年々ツイートしてもらえたら、
Too late already. If you guys could tweet about stuff like that year by year,
ツイートしてもらえると嬉しいと思うので、ぜひぜひみなさんよろしくお願いします！
I'd be really happy, so everyone, please do!
はい、というわけでね、今日はね、最初歌だったんですけど、
Right, so, today, we started with songs, but
歌以外にも実はこういうなんかありまして、ええ、この5年間、5周年でもあるので、の年表っていうのを私ちょっと作ってみまして、
besides singing, there's actually something like this—well, since it's also the 5-year anniversary, I made a timeline of these 5 years,
見るんだ。それね。そう、で、
You're gonna look at it. Right. So,
みんなと同じイベントとか、ライブもあるので、その話とかをしていけたらいいなと思っております。
since we've shared events and lives together, I hope we can talk about those kinds of things.
逆に仲良くなって振り返ったりとかないですか？ないよね。それちゃんの配信で振り返らさせてもらうわ。
Have you guys ever looked back on things after getting closer? Probably not. I'll just look back on it during Sora-chan's streams.
そうそうそう。ついでに、思い出してちょっと、大体。はい。で、前半は、白ちゃん戸みとちゃんに、
Yeah, exactly. Reminisce along the way, roughly. Right. So, the first half is with Shiro-chan and Mito-chan,
そして後半は葵ちゃんとゆいちゃん。ちょっとね、
and the second half is with Aoi-chan and Yui-chan. So,
後半色々あって、なんか、友利ちゃんとゆいちゃんって一緒じゃない？だからもっとかもしれないけど。
in the second half, a lot happened, and aren't Tomori-chan and Yui-chan together? So maybe even more.
でもね、後でね、またごに集まるところもあるかもしれないので、よろしくお願いします！
But hey, we might all gather again later, so please look forward to it!
というわけで、さあ、続年表に、行っちゃいましょう！
And with that, let's head right into the continuation timeline!
というわけで、ときのそら年表、前半はこちらの2人にいってもらってます！
So, for the first half of Tokino Sora's timeline, these two will take us through it!
こんにちは、私、ツモです。そして、
Hello, I am Tsumo. And—
おっと？
Oh?
よろしくお願いいたします。
Pleased to meet you.
よろしくお願いいたします。なんかすごい、こんなに落ち着きだったのかなさっきまで。
Pleased to meet you. Wow, were they this calm until just now?
情報番組だから。
Because it's an information program.
情報番組、いらっしゃって聞いて聞いてきたんで、え、違うんですか？
An information program? That's what we heard, wait, is it not?
違うんですよ。ちょっと一緒に年表を見っていきたいなと思っております。
It's not. We want to look through the timeline together.
はい、前半はね、
Right, the first half,
そうそうそう。
yeah, yeah, yeah.
私がデビューした2017年の9月から2019万、へと、なっております。
spans from September 2017 when I debuted, up to 2019.
2017年。
2017.
はい、そうだ。
Yes, that's right.
当時のね、なんかVTuberって言うと、全然、もう、ここのメンバーと、
Back then, when you said "VTuber," there weren't nearly as many people
ね、今日ね、ほかに来てくれる後半組の子、とかみたいにそんなにいっぱいいなかったじゃん。
like the members here today or the second-half group coming later.
え、だってさ、30人以内だったよ、絶対。
Right? There were definitely under 30 people!
そうそうそうそうそう。今こそホロライブさんが運ばれて呼ばれているように、VTuberみんなが、
Exactly, exactly. Just like how Hololive is being carried and called upon now, back then,
ちょっと箱みたいな雰囲気が、
all VTubers had a cozy, box-like vibe to them—
あ、ね、そうだったね。
Ah, yeah, that's right.
でもね、そんな私たちそれぞれ後輩もね、もうできる立場になっちゃってて、
But you know, we're now in a position where we each have juniors of our own,
間違いなく。いや、みんな箱持ちというか、
without a doubt. Everyone's box-holders, so to speak—
そんなことないです。
No way, that's not it!
今回ね見るのは、私たち前半ということで、
This time, what we're looking at is our first half,
まだねそのVTuberっていうのが知られて間もない時期の年表ということになっていますので、
so it's a timeline of a period when VTubers weren't very well known yet.
なんかインターネットカチカチオタクだった時の、
Back when everyone was a hardcore internet nerd,
みんなの見 てってたっていう、
everyone was watching everyone else—
楽しみ。ね。
I'm looking forward to it. Yeah.
そのときのやつはぜひね、見ていけたらいいなと思っているので、
I hope we can look back at those times together,
では早速年表を見ていきましょう！まずは、こちらです！
so let's check out the timeline right away! First up is this!
#ときのそら年表 1年目 (2017年9月-2018年8月)
[#Tokino Sora Timeline: Year 1 (Sep 2017 - Aug 2018)]
こちら私の1年目となっておりまして、
This is my first year,
これ、あれですか？隠してあるんですか？あ、そうなんです。
Is this... hidden? Ah, yes, it is.
一緒に話せそうだな、って思う場所とか、
Places where we thought we could talk about things together,
おー,なんかちょっと こういうふうに ちょっと赤くしてあるので
Oh, sort of, like this, making it a bit red, so...
え,すでにみえてるところだけでお腹いっぱいというか全部話せるとは思えないけど
Um, just seeing what's already visible is overwhelming... I don't think we can cover everything, but
ま,まずはね,一個目から見ていきたいと思います。
Well, first of all, let's look at the very first one.
えー一個目?どれかな?
Um, the first one? Which one is it?
もう一個目だからね。うん。
Well, since it's the first one. Yeah.
え,一番目は こちらです。
Um, the very first one is right here.
おーそうだやっぱり。
Oh, that's right, of course.
そう,バーチャルJKとしてね,ときのそら初ニコニコ生放送だったんですよね。
Right, as a virtual JK, it was Tokino Sora's first Nico Nico Live broadcast.
え,あ,初めてはYouTubeじゃなくて,最初の数ヶ月はニコニコ生放送だったので
The very first wasn't YouTube; for the first few months it was Nico Nico Live, so...
そう,YouTubeに来たのは結構遅いですよね?
That's right, coming to YouTube was quite late, wasn't it?
もちろん存じております。
Of course I am aware of it.
あ,ありがとうございます。
Ah, thank you very much.
もちろん。
Of course.
ねえ。
Right?
実は こちら,その一一番最初の映像がね,なんと用意されているということなので
Actually, the very first video footage is surprisingly prepared for us, so...
ちょっと見てみましょう!
let's take a look!
どうぞ!
Here we go!
うわ,見えてますか?映ってますか?
Whoa, can you see me? Is it showing?
声届いてますかね?可愛い。
Is my voice reaching you? So cute.
いや,でもこれさ,BGMもないって本当におかしくない?
No, but isn't it really weird that there's no BGM?
確かに出ないんだ。
That's true, it really doesn't.
え,ちょっとさ,何ゆきちゃった感じで。
Um, kind of like, what did I say?
大丈夫そう?ねえ。
Seems okay? Hey.
ま,まずはJKだからこう手動く時。
Well, first as a JK, moving my hands like this.
あ,皆さんこんばんは!そして初めまして。
Ah, good evening everyone! And nice to meet you.
もう頑張って元気な顔を出そうとしてる感がすごい。2000年生まれの女子高生です。
You can really feel the effort to put on an energetic face. I'm a high school girl born in 2000.
え,本当 に?初めての配信なので,今日はちょっと気合いが入ってます。
Eh, really? Since it's my first stream, I'm feeling extra spirited today.
まあ,髪型とかね,はね,もっとクリアえー,なんか本当に
Well, my hair and stuff was more clear, and like, really...
なんかあか抜けてない感があるというか
It kind of has a vibe of not being polished yet, or...
ちょっとお,濃い感じ?
A bit, oh, heavy-looking?
何で言ったそんなに!
Why'd you say that much!
何? えー濃い。やっぱり今は垢抜けたって言いたいんです。
What? Eh, heavy. I mean, I want to say I've become more polished now.
いじわるばっかだな。
You're just being mean.
そしてそして
And then, and then
2017年はね,あの間にハロウィンがあったり,あん肝が出てきたりとあったんですが
In 2017, there was Halloween in between, and Ankimo appeared, among other things,
まあそのあとね,次のパネルがあるのでちょっと見てみましょう。
but after that, there's the next panel, so let's take a look.
あー,あ,実はね,クリスマスが初めてのYouTubeなんですよ。
Ah, actually, Christmas was the very first YouTube stream.
だいぶ長いことニコニコ生放送だったんですよね。
It was Nico Nico Live for quite a long time.
あ,そうなの。
Ah, is that so.
え,そうなの。二人は初めてのYouTubeをやった時って初めてのYouTubeの生放送をやった時ってどんな感じだった?
Eh, is that so. How did you two feel when you did your first YouTube live broadcast?
あ,私結構早いですよ。もうその次からYouTubeだったと思います。
Ah, I was pretty early. I think it was YouTube right after that.
あーそっかそっかそっか。二足の草鞋というか。
Ah, I see, I see. Wearing two pairs of shoes, so to speak.
そうですね,あのもう,凛先輩とかに教えてもらってやったって感じですね。誰も知なくて,裏方のほうがYouTubeの
That's right, um, I was taught by Rin-senpai and did it that way. Nobody knew, and behind the scenes, YouTube's...
JK組でね。
As the JK group.
そうか,そうか。
I see, I see.
私も知らなかった。
I didn't know either.
なるほど。白は,さっき裏でそらちゃんと喋ったんですけど
I see. Shiro, earlier backstage I talked with Sora-chan, but
あの,初配信をファンの方をね,あの電動世界にね,飛ばそうっていうイメージある?
um, did you have the image of sending fans into the virtual world for the first stream?
え,嬉しいステッカーってやったら
Eh, if you do a happy sticker,
ファンの方だけ巨大化したり,天井から吊られちゃったりする魔法があって,白喋りながらファンがどんどん巨大化していったり
there's magic where only fans become gigantic or get hung from the ceiling, and while Shiro talks, fans keep getting bigger and bigger,
ファンがなんかフックに吊されてデッドバイデイライトの世界で
and fans get hung on hooks in the Dead by Daylight world,
殺人鬼の気持ちで,もう何だっていいな。あの,いつ捕まれるんだろうって生きとここちがいいよ
feeling like a serial killer, anything is fine. Like, 'When will I be caught?' It feels alive.
いやいや,でもなんか.
No, no, but somehow...
いやね,それぞれもね,やっぱりね,やっぱり初めての生放送,こう聞くとね,全然違う感じするよね。
Well, you know, for each of us, listening to our first live broadcasts like this, it feels completely different.
歴史ありですね。歴史あるね。
There's history there. There is history.
そしてそして,次がパネルになってますが,次は こちらです。
And then, the next panel is up, but the next one is this.
おー!
Whoa!
はい,ということで ここでね,チャンネル登録者が10万人という ことになっております。
Yes, so here, channel subscribers reached 100,000.
いや結構早いんだなと思った。
Man, I thought it was pretty fast.
確かに,え,だってさ活動を始めた時この時期に10万人って思ってないですよね。
That's true. I mean, when I started activities, I wouldn't have thought 100,000 in this period.
思ってんの。てか,なんか1万も行くかなぐらいの感覚だったから。
I didn't think so. I felt like, 'Would it even reach 10,000?'
ねえ。
Right?
ま,でもこの後はね,いろんなところでコラボとかいろんな人と会うようになってきてて
Well, but after this, I started doing collaborations and meeting various people in different places,
まあ,あおいちゃんとも初めてコラボしたりとか,あとね絆愛ちゃんの誕生日イベントに
well, collaborating with Aoi-chan for the first time, and also at Kizuna Ai-chan's birthday event,
覚えてる?
Do you remember?
覚えてる。
I remember.
あ,お二人もね,出てらっしゃいましたもんね。
Ah, you two appeared there too, right?
うんうんうんうん。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
ここからね,あそこから七歳に
From here, um, starting from 7 years old...
いたいよね。
I want to be.
私見てましたからね,私達は。
I was watching, after all.
え,でもね,いないのが意外なぐらい,もう2000 いやもう出てきた時から
Eh, but you know, it's surprising how you weren't there, since 2000... no, from the very beginning,
すごかった。すごい感動的でしたよ,見てる方からしたら。
it was amazing. It was so touching from the viewer's perspective.
なんか,あの,愛ちゃんのガチャッシャが現場で,あ,壊されてみんな人間の指令とかピョコピョコついて
Like, um, Ai-chan's gachashah was broken on site, and everyone had human commands and was hopping around,
なんかみんな愛ちゃんって何だっけ?記憶にあります。
and everyone was like 'What is Ai-chan?' I remember.
というわけでね,ね,2年目に行く前に
So, before going into the 2nd year,
今回その年ごとにですね,メッセージをいただいておりまして。
this time we received messages for each year.
あの,1年目は2017年,最初にね,あの見えてますかー?ってさっき
Um, the 1st year is 2017, at first, um, 'Can you see meー?' earlier
あの,出てた,1年目のスタイリスト,2017年のスタイリストをお,やってくださった因幡先生からのメッセージが届いておりますので,読みたいと思います!お願いします!
um, the stylist from the 1st year, Inaba-sensei, who worked on the 2017 style, sent us a message, so I'd like to read it! Please!
ときのそらさんへ
To Tokino Sora-san,
初期のそらのデザインとモデリングをさせていただきました、いかきです。
I'm Ika-ki, who designed and modeled Sora's original look.
このたびはYouTube登録者数100万人、たいへんおめでとうございます！
Huge congratulations on reaching 1 million YouTube subscribers!
おめでとうございます！
Congratulations!
これまでの軌跡を追っていらっしゃる伺って、拙いながらも筆を取らせていただきました。
Hearing that you're tracing your past milestones inspired me to write this, however clumsily.
…せっかくですので、すこし思い出話をしようかと思います。
...Since I have the chance, I thought I'd share a few memories.
ふと記憶を思い返してみると、あれからもうすぐ6年が経つようです。
Looking back, it seems almost 6 years have passed since then.
最近では、日々大きくなっていくそらちゃんとホロライブの羽ばたきが目に染みます。
Lately, I've been deeply moved watching Sora-chan and Hololive grow larger day by day.
活動を始めてからの年を数えるにも、もうすぐ片手では足りなくなってしまうんですね。感慨深いです。
Counting the years since activities began, one hand will soon no longer be enough. It's deeply emotional.
実は初めて名前を知ったのは、デビュー直前にふとTwitterで目にした告知ツイートでした。
Actually, the first time I learned your name was right before your debut, in an announcement tweet I happened to see on Twitter.
その時の私は嬉しい気持ちと、驚きが混ざった心境でした。
At that time, my feelings were a mix of joy and surprise.
今ではホロライブのアイドルとして、走り続けて止まらないそらちゃんですが、デザイン当時は名前すらなく、「バーチャルJK」というキーワードがあるだけでした。
Now Sora-chan is an unstoppable idol running onward as part of Hololive, but back when she was designed, she didn't even have a name—just the keyword "Virtual JK."
デザインから3Dモデルの完成まで1ヶ月弱という期間でしたが、私の中には「爽やかな学園アニメのような」「清で穏やかな」「よく晴れた早朝の空」というキーワードが固まっていました。
From design to completed 3D model took less than a month, but in my mind, keywords like "like a refreshing school anime," "pure and gentle," and "a bright, clear early morning sky" had solidified.
どうでしょう、今のそらちゃんにもピッタリだと思いませんか？
What do you think? Don't you think it fits the current Sora-chan perfectly?
これらのキーワードに合わせてデザインしていたので、「デザインから読み取っていただけたのかな…？」と思えるほどぴたりの印象だったんです。天才ですね笑
I designed her around these keywords, so the impression was so spot-on that I thought, "Did they pick up on that from the design...?" She's a genius, haha.
さて、配信活動が始まってからしばらく経ったあとのお話、一時期、私には自信をなくしていた頃がありました。
Now, moving on to a story from some time after streaming began, there was a period when I was losing confidence.
先ほどお話しした初期の衣装デザインには、もう一つだけ盛り込んだキーワードがあります。それは…「無個性で、未完成な」今のそらちゃんからは思いつかないイメージですね。
The early costume design I mentioned earlier has just one more keyword packed into it. That is... "devoid of personality, unfinished." It's an image you wouldn't associate with today's Sora-chan at all.
当初、地味で華やかさの少ないデザインだったかと思います。当時の私はそらちゃんの個性を演出したい！という未来にかける希望よりも、持たせたい印象を優先してしまったのです。
Back then, I think her design was plain and lacking in flashiness. At the time, rather than hope for the future—wanting to bring out Sora-chan's individuality—I prioritized the impression I wanted to give her.
少し視点は違うかもしれませんが、ご自分を「水」と例えていたそらちゃんの苦悩は自分に通ずるところがありました。
Though our perspectives might be slightly different, Sora-chan once compared herself to "water," and her struggles resonated with me.
ふと目に入ってしまった心無いコメントで傷ついたことがあれば、完璧なモデルに仕上げることができなかったことも、
If I was hurt by unfeeling comments that caught my eye, and couldn't craft her into a flawless model...
周りを見れば素敵なクリエイターさんばかりで劣等感に苛まれる日々です。
Looking around at all the wonderful creators made me feel tormented by inferiority every day.
考えれば考えるほどに「こうなるなら自分が担当させていただくべきではなかった」という気持ちすらありました。
The more I thought about it, the more I even felt, "If it was going to turn out like this, I shouldn't have been the one in charge."
しかし、結局そんな苦悩からもそらちゃんやそらともさんに救われました。
However, ultimately, even from those struggles, I was saved by Sora-chan and the Soratomos.
思い返してみればどうでしょう、いつだって前に進もうと挫けず立ち向かう一生懸命さと強さ、透き通った心地良い歌声にも、何度も勇気をいただきました。
Looking back, how is it? I received courage time and time again from your hard work and strength to always keep moving forward without yielding, and your clear, comforting singing voice.
立派な個性で堂々と活動しているそらちゃんはいつだって眩しいです。それを見守るそらともさんも皆暖かく、
Sora-chan, active with splendid individuality and pride, is always dazzling. And the Soratomos watching over you are all so warm,
ありのままを喜んで楽しんでいらっしゃって…
rejoicing and enjoying things just as they are...
3周年ライブのときにふと、ずっと引きずっていた自分が急に恥ずかしくなったんです。
At the 3rd-anniversary live, I suddenly felt embarrassed of myself for holding onto that baggage for so long.
…目の前で輝く歌姫にサイリウムを振って応援しては感動し、
...Waving penlights and feeling moved while supporting the shining songstress right before my eyes,
日々の配信では、画面の前で同じゲームで遊んでは笑って、
laughing while playing the same games in front of the screen during daily streams,
新しい衣装や誕生日、記念日には自分のことのように喜んでではイラストを描いたり、
rejoicing over new outfits, birthdays, and anniversaries as if they were my own and drawing illustrations,
新曲の動画の公開を心待ちにしたり、
eagerly awaiting new song releases,
ファン作品を観て、聴いて、感激したり、
being moved by fan works,
時には不器用にとらともさんとコミュニケーションをしてみたり…
and awkwardly communicating with Soratomos...
語りきれないですが、たくさんの思い出はどれも本当に楽しい時間でした。
I can't talk about it all, but all these countless memories were truly wonderful times.
きットほかのそらともさんも、それぞれに素敵な思い出があることかと思います。
I'm sure every other Soratomo has their own wonderful memories as well.
どれもすべて、そらさんから生まれたんです。
Every single one of them was born from Sora-san.
あなたの熱量に集まった、たくさんの「思い出」。それがあるからこそ、
The countless "memories" gathered by your passion. Because of those,
0から歩みを進めてきたあなたが、「今」という大舞台にたどり着くことができた理由なんだなと、私は確信しています。
I am certain that is the reason why you, who advanced step by step from zero, were able to reach the grand stage of "now."
本当に素敵な旅路が残っていますよ。
Truly wonderful journeys lie ahead.
いまこの時をご一緒できて心から嬉しいです。
I am sincerely happy to share this moment with you right now.
改めて、100万人おめでとうございます。
Once again, congratulations on 1 million subscribers.
山盛りいっぱいの感謝を いかき
With a mountain of gratitude, Ika-ki.
はい、どうですか？そらちゃん。
Yes, how is it, Sora-chan?
いやぁ…
Well...
なんだろ…？
What could it be...?
そらっ父さんしかいないんだから！
Because it's only Sora-tousan!
いやぁ…！いや、こんなに、なんか、たくさんの…
Whoa...! I never thought I would receive...
ね、メッセージをいただけると…
so many messages, you know...
思ってなかっただし、なんか…「あ、こんな風に応援してくださってるんだなぁ」
I really didn't expect it... seeing for the first time how people were cheering for me like this...
っていうのを初めて見たので、なんかちょっと…
made me feel a bit... um...
そらちゃん、目から美しい水が、ぶわぁって流れているんですが…
Sora-chan, beautiful water is just gushing from your eyes...
本当になんかね、すごいそらちゃんとは違った視点でね…
It's really amazing, from a perspective so different from Sora-chan's...
そらちゃんの歩みを体験されてて、またそらっ父さんともちょっと違った視点でも思ってらっしゃるからさ、ねぇ。
experiencing Sora-chan's journey with a perspective different even from Sora-tousan's, you know.
なんかすごいそっちにも物語があるってね…
It makes you realize there's a whole story over there too...
なんかすごいそっちにも物語があるってね、感激しましたね！
I was really moved by that!
いやぁ、なんか、え、こちらこそですよ、なんか…
Oh, um, well, the feeling is mutual, you know...
なんて言うんだろ、その…ね、
how should I put it... um...
確かに私は、今もですけど、そこまで強い個性はないとは思ってるんですけど…
It's true that even now, I don't think I have a particularly strong personality...
でも、その、私が一番私らしいと思ってたし、最初の私が一番好きというか…
But I always thought I was most myself, or rather, I loved my initial self the most...
最初の私を見た瞬間から、私は私らしく、本当に…
From the moment I first saw myself, I've truly been myself...
あぁ、私として生まれてきて17年間よかったなと思ってるので、
and I'm so glad I was born as myself for these 17 years,
17歳になってデビューできたのは本当に私にとっての宝物なので、
so being able to debut at 17 is truly a treasure to me,
こんな風に言っていただけるの本当にありがたいです。ありがとうございます！
and I'm so grateful to hear you say that. Thank you so much!
いやー本当のこと…ねえ！
Yeah, it's the truth... right!
以上、1年目でした！
That wraps up year one!
いや、1年目だけでもだいぶ恋いですね！
Man, year one alone is already so intense!
そうですねえ。で、そんな中で、こう、いろいろね、VTuberが世界に…
That's right. And amidst all that, VTubers started becoming known to the world...
世界というかみんなに知ってもらえるようになって、2年目が始まるというわけですが、そちら2年目の年表いってみましょう！こちらです。
or rather, to everyone, and now year two is about to begin. Let's check out the year two timeline! Here it is.
はい、というわけでね、こちらの2年目のパネルはちょっと長いんですけど…
Yes, so the panel for the second year is quite long...
文字が多いですね。
There's a lot of text.
そうですね、まあそこはね、一気にめくっちゃおうと思いますので、いけ！こちらです！
Yeah, so let's flip through it all at once! Here we go!
ここではイベントとかアニメがいっぱいあった時期、ニコニコ超パーティー2018バーチャル大晦日に出演、アニメ『バーチャルさんはさんでいる』#1が放送、どーーーん！！の時期ですね。
This was a time full of events and anime: appearing at Niconico Chokaigi Party 2018 and Virtual New Year's Eve, and the broadcast of the anime "Virtual-san Looking" Episode 1, boom!!
濃いなぁ…濃いですね！
So intense... It really is!
違ったね、なんか形で我々にも関わってくる話ですもんね。
In a way, it's a story that also involves us.
そうそうそうそう。そしてね、ニコニコ超パーティー2018の映像があるということなので、それを見たいなと思います。どうぞ！
Exactly, exactly. And since there's footage from Niconico Chokaigi Party 2018, let's take a look at it. Here it is!
はい、というわけでね、こちらニコニコ超パーティー、これさいたまスーパーアリーナ！
Yes, so here is Niconico Chokaigi Party at Saitama Super Arena!
ということでみんな出てるんですよ、ここ。ね！でね、なんかいや、こんな大きい場所でパフォーマンスしたの初めてだったから…！
Everyone performed here, you know! And since it was my first time performing in such a huge place...
ねぇ…！緊張したんだよね、2人はどうだった？
Right... We were so nervous. How about you two?
初めてでしたよ、私もこんな大きい場所でやるの。
It was my first time performing in such a huge place too.
確かに！めっちゃ緊張しましたよ。
True! I was super nervous.
本当に大人を…って思って…大人にね、そうそうそうそう！
I felt like there were so many adults... yeah, exactly!
なんか白上フブキちゃんを歌わせていただいたんですけど、歌ったら女の子の声もたくさん返ってきて、会場と歌うっていう、なんかやり取りができたのが覚えていますね。
I got to sing with Shirakami Fubuki-chan, and when I sang, lots of girls' voices echoed back, and I remember interacting with the venue through song.
確かに。やっぱ歓声とかあるとね、やっぱね、嬉しくなるよね。
True. When there are cheers like that, it really makes you happy.
まあ、2019年は、ビクターエンタテインメントからメジャーデビューが決まったりだとか、
Well, in 2019, my major debut from Victor Entertainment was decided,
あと『わたぬきさんちの』っていうドラマに出させていただいたりとか…
and I got to appear in a drama called "Watanuki-san Chi no"...
三姉妹で！
As three sisters!
そうです、そうです、そうです。あとはですね、あの、デビューアルバムが、そう、ちょうどね3月27日に発売されたりとか…
That's right, exactly. And my debut album was released right around March 27th...
そういうことがありましての、次なんですけど…
After all of that, moving on to the next thing...
なんだろ、気になる！
I wonder what it is, I'm curious!
そして次がこちらですね。『重大発表と大事なお知らせ最後まで見てね』っていう放送だったんですけど、
And next is this one. It was a broadcast titled "Major Announcement and Important Notice, Watch Until the End!"
映像がありますので、何が重大発表だったのかちょっと見てもらいたいと思います。どうぞ！
We have footage of it, so I'd like you to see what the major announcement was. Here you go!
やったーーー！
Yayyy!
というわけでですね、ここで、えー、1番、あ、そう、ワンマンライブを決定したというのと…
So basically, here, um, deciding on my first solo live show...
この時にちょっとお化粧ができるようになってまして…
Around this time, I became able to put on some makeup...
おめでとう！
Congratulations!
まだAちゃんがこの…ちょっと絵心も成長しちゃっていう…！
A-chan's artistic sense was still growing back then...
足がね、あ、色がついて…
My legs got colored...
そう、色がついてね、ちょっと手もね、ちょっと進化してっていうね。まあ自分のお化粧、Aちゃんがちょっとお化粧が…
Yeah, they got colored, and my hands evolved a bit too. My makeup... A-chan's makeup...
あと、あの、ライブが決まったみたいな…
And also, like, the live show being decided...
ってあった時ということで
...at the time, so...
ソラちゃんって言ったらやっぱりステージでアイドルとして歌って魅了してっていう印象がもうしっかり確立されてるので、
When you think of Sora-chan, the image of her singing and captivating people as an idol on stage is already firmly established.
そうですよね、やっぱ、
That's right, and...
ここが時のソラちゃんの1人の重大なステージの発表会だったんだなって、うん、大事な日付ですね。
This was such a major milestone for Tokino Sora-chan... It's an important date.
そうだね。なんかここはやっぱり応援してくれてるソラともさんも、なんか6月27日になると最初から応援してくれてるファンの一人は色々思い出すみたいな、
That's true. For the Sora-tomo who have been supporting her from the start, June 27th probably brings back a lot of memories.
へえー、なんか色々あるみたいなのね。なんかターニングポイント1つ目というか、まあ、1つ目は、
There are probably all kinds of things. It's like the first turning point—well, maybe the first one...
色々あるかもしれないけど1番大きかったかなあと思いますね。
There might be others, but I think it was the biggest one.
そんな2年目なんですけど、
That's her 2nd year, but...
もうね、ある方からメッセージをいただいているので、ちょっとビデオレター見てみたいなと思います。
since we've received messages from certain people, let's watch the video together!
ですか？この方です！
Is that so? Here is that person!
ガキゲンダよ！
Gaki-genga dayo!
スペースジンルイさん！
Spacejinrui-san!
侵略宇宙人、銀河アリスです！
Shinryaku-uchuujin, Ginga Alice desu!
アリスさまー！ ソラちゃん！ソラちゃん！
Alice-sama! Sora-chan! Sora-chan!
100万人さま、こんにちは記念！
Happy 1 million subscribers anniversary!
おめでとうございアリスーー！
Congratulations, Alice-sama!
すごいや！
That's amazing!
すごすぎるよ！
That's incredible!
100万人って、何人ですか？
1 million subscribers? How many people is that?
100万人だよ！
1 million people!
なんかさ、たくさんの人がソラちゃん大好きってことはバッチリ伝わってきてます！すごいです！
It's clear that so many people truly love Sora-chan. That's amazing.
あの、ソラちゃんと初めてお会いした時、緊張していたね、アリスを、
Also, when Alice first met Sora-chan, Alice was very nervous...
とっても優しく包み込んでくださって、秒で匿名たことを今でも覚えています。
and Sora-chan gently wrapped her up in kindness, and Alice still remembers that she was anonymous in an instant.
ありがとう！ニコバーウトボリュームワンで、初めてイベントさんにね、一緒に、出場させていただいたんですけど、
Thank you! At "Cho-Vtuber Volume 1", it was the first time Alice appeared at an event together with other VTubers.
かわいくって、みんなに楽しんでもらいたいっていう気持ちに溢れたソラちゃんのステージさんは、最高すぎました！もう、最高オブ最高でした！
Sora-chan's stage, filled with the desire to be cute and let everyone have fun, was simply too wonderful! It was the absolute best!
なんかね、あのソラちゃんがアリスのダンスを見て自分もダンスを頑張りたいって思ってくださってって聞いて、本当に嬉しかったんですけど、
It made Alice think, "Seeing Sora-chan's dance makes me want to dance hard too!" and she was truly happy.
アリスも、あのソラちゃんのね、最強の歌たさんをこうすごく間近で聴いたりとか、ときに可愛く、ときにカッコよく、もうのびのびソラちゃんが歌っている姿を見て、歌たさんをね、頑張りたいってアリスも思えた一つのきっかけだったので、
And Alice was also given a great opportunity to listen to Sora-chan's strongest songs up close, and to watch Sora-chan sing so vibrantly, cutely, and coolly, which made Alice want to work hard on her own songs too.
なんかさ、もう、すごいじゃん！
So, you know, it was really amazing!
また一緒にね、ソラリストとしてステージさんに立たせていただきたいね。
Once again, Alice wants to stand on stage as a Soralist and face stage-san!
そして、ソラとものみなさん！お、アリスもソラともですから、これからも一緒にね、ソラちゃんについて行いましょう！
And to all the Sora-tomo out there—Alice is also a Sora-tomo, so let's continue to follow along with Sora-chan!
改めてソラちゃん、本当に本当におめでとうございます！これからも素敵なところはずっとそのままで、この先さらにさらに進化していくお姿を近くで応援させてください！
To Sora-chan, truly, truly congratulations on your 1 million subscribers! May your wonderful qualities continue just as they are, and please let us cheer you on closely as you evolve even further in the future!
ずっと、ずーーっと大好きです！それじゃあ、バイバーイ！
Always, always love you! So, Sora-chan, bye-bye!
ありがとう！
Thank you!
元気でしたね。
She was so energetic!
元気だったね。
She was full of energy!
すっごいじゃん。
So cute!
銀河アリスちゃん、幼馴染みみたいな。
Ginga Alice-chan... It's like they're childhood friends.
そう、で、でね、あの「すっごいじゃん」っていうのは、やっぱり、なんかいつも通りのアリスちゃんが会って、いいなと思った。
Yeah, yeah, yeah! And you know, "So, so, so amazing!" is just like Alice-chan, which made me think, "How nice."
アリスちゃんとはね、この今も言ってかった通り、チュウバートっていう初めて一緒にね、なんか対談みたいな感じで、
And with Alice-chan, this was our very first time doing a talk show and livestream together like this,
ライブをさせていただいて、私のダンスを頑張ろうと思ったきっかけのを作ってくれたっていうのもあるし、すごい仲のいいお友達なので、何にね、ライブさんとかさんをつけるところがめちゃくちゃ可愛くて、
and she even created the catalyst for me to try harder with my dancing! We're close friends, so she even puts "Live-san" or "-san" on things, which is super cute.
今回はね、メッセージをいただいちゃいました。ありがとうございます！
So this time, we received a message from her. Thank you so much!
というわけで、2年目まで終わりましたが、どうですかね、2年目まで。
So, that brings us to the end of the 2nd year. How do you feel about it up to the 2nd year?
後ろ、お伺いしてて思ったのが、多分ドラマの撮影もですけど、ほぼ丸一日撮影にかけたり、
Well, looking back, what I thought was that, besides probably filming dramas, we spent almost round-the-clock time filming,
ソラともを喜ばせるための取り組みでなんだかんだ睡眠時間の趣味の時間も取れなかったんじゃないですか？
and it was all an effort to make Sora-tomo happy, so despite everything, we probably didn't get much sleep or free time, right?
でも二人だって、いっぱい色々出てて大変だった時期だったんじゃない？
But with two of us, so many things came up and it must have been a really tough period, right?
やっぱそのつらさが分かるのは、
Yeah, I know how hard that is, so...
わー！そうそうそう！
That's right!
おいで！おいで！
Come here! Come here!
あ、ごめん、ぶつかっちゃった。
Ah, wait, I bumped into the stool.
あ、ちょっとね、同期ダンスしようもんなんで同期ダンス。どういうことなん、ソラちゃん真ん中。
And since we both wanted to do a synchronized dance, we ended up right in the middle!
え？何？どういうこと？
What, what, what?
真ん中だけど、
Right in the middle, but...
右と左にさ、
On the right and left...
これがあれ、これが同期ダンス！これが同期ダンス！
That's synchronized! That's synchronized!
じゃあこんな同期ダンスをしながら今日この会話を終わりにしましょうかね。ありがとうございます！
So, doing this synchronized dance, let's bring today's chat to a close! Thank you so much!
同期っていいな！
It's good to be synchronized, so good!
おめでとうございます
Congratulations.
あとに入れるかい？
Shall we go in afterwards?
二人ともありがとうございます！
Thank you both so much!
こちらこそ、ありがとうございます！
No, thank you so much!
おめでとうございまーす！
Congratulations!
二人にはね、あとでもう1曲、歌って貰ってもいいですか？
Can we have you two sing another song later?
歌ってもらってもいいですか？歌いましょう、お願いします！
Please sing with us! We'd love that!
よろしくお願いします！
Please look forward to it!
それではこのテンションで後半に向かいます！
With that energy, let's head into the second half!
うおおおー！
Woooo!
はい、というわけで後半パートは、アキちゃんと、AZKiちゃんでーす！
Yes, so for the second half, we have Aki-chan and AZKi-chan!
いぇーい！
Yay!
アキです。やってる。隠されてる、はずされてる。
It's Aki. We're doing it. It's hidden, it's removed.
はい、というわけでね。
Yes, so...
ここからは3年目、2019年あたりからのをね、おっと、近づいてきましたね。見ていきたいと思うので。
From here, looking at the 3rd year, around 2019—whoops, we're getting closer. Let's take a look.
じゃあ早速、3年目のパネルを見てみましょう！こちらでーす！
So let's check out the panel for year 3! Here it is!
ま、3年目はね、ちょっとあれなんですよ。あのね、ほら、世界でもいろんなことがあって、いろんなものが変わった時代ということで、
Well, year 3 is a bit... you know, see, a lot of things happened around the world, and many things changed during that time,
ちょっとね、ちょっと少なめの時期にはなってるんですけども、まあね。
so it's a bit of a sparse period, but still.
そんな中で2019年にあったものがね、あるのでちょっとそれを見たいと思います。それがこちらです、なんだろう？
In the midst of that, there's something from 2019, so let's take a look. Here it is, what is it?
えー、10月6日にね、初のワンマンライブDream！開催があったんですけど、なんとね、これ前日に2人がライブをしてるんですよね。
Um, on October 6th, the first solo live 'Dream!' was held, but amazingly, the two of them had a live concert the day before.
そうなんですよ。そうなのよね。
That's right. That's true.
昼の部を、昼の部やって、いつかの昼の部、夜の部、次の日...
Doing the daytime show, and then someday the daytime show, nighttime show, the next day...
こう連続でっていうのが話題になった。
Doing it consecutively became a hot topic.
そうなんだよね。
That's right.
だからなんかね、そこすごい一致団結して感じあるよね。あした頑張って、別々に分かれてるけど一緒みたいなのすごいしましたね。
So it felt like everyone was really united. Even though we were in separate places tomorrow, it felt like we were together.
本当にそうだった。そうなんだよね。で、リハーサルとかさ、結構ね、時間かぶることがあって。
It really was. That's right. And rehearsals and stuff often overlapped in time.
そう、で、特にここ一緒だったからさ、日取りが。だから、なんかAZKiがリハーサル終わったあとに、アキがリハーサルとかあって
Right, especially since these dates were the same. So, like, after AZKi finished her rehearsal, Aki had her rehearsal,
そのときにさ、ま、1個話すならさ、なんかAZKiが一瞬ちょっとはけたんだよね、ステージから。で戻ったら、
and at that time, to share one story, AZKi briefly left the stage for a second. And when she came back,
なんかちょっとあの、AZKiの髪の毛なくなってて、頭が。でそれをアキにいにして、ねえ見て、頭ツルツルになったって言ったら、
somehow, AZKi's hair was gone, her head was bald. And she showed that to Aki, saying 'Hey look, my head became completely smooth!'
体張りすぎだろ！って言って、バトンタッチしたことあったね。
And I said, 'You're pushing your body too hard!' and we passed the baton.
そう、そのあとにソラちゃんがね、やるっていう。そうそうそう。
Right, and after that Sora-chan does it. That's right.
もしかしたら、もうちょっとね、ソラも、ちょっと頭ツルツルになってたかも。本当に、そういえば本当にかかった、かかってたらね。
Maybe Sora's head was also a bit smooth too. Really, come to think of it, if it had really happened.
じゃあね、そういうのかかってるかどうかの当時の映像をね、見てみましょうかね！
So let's check out the footage from back then to see if that actually happened!
好き、泣いちゃいそうだ
I feel like crying from love
いやあいい曲。完璧な聞こえが 言ってたよねー。
Ah, such a good song. It sounded so perfect. You were saying that!
なんか、初めてワンマンやって、もっと歌ってきたいなって私は思ったんだよね。
Like, having done my first solo live, I thought to myself that I want to sing even more.
ああ、嬉しい。
Aww, I'm so happy.
いい日じゃん、いい日じゃん。もう最高の一番の思い出の日。
Such a good day, a wonderful day. The best, most memorable day.
ベスト5に入る。あの、10月6日ベスト5に入りますよ、もちろん。夢だったからね、ライブやるの。
It goes into the top 5. October 6th is definitely in the top 5. Because it was my dream to hold a live concert.
本当にね、そうよね。
Truly, that's right.
そしてね、この3年目なんだけど、ビデオレターがちょっとある方から届いているということで、誰？ちょっと見てみたいと思います。こちらです！
And, for this 3rd year, we received a video letter from someone special. Who is it? Let's take a look. Here it is!
お、でた！そらの、そらちゃーん！
Oh, it's—! Sora's, Sora-chan!
イェーイ！てぇてぇとね、だ、イェーイ！そらちゃん、100万人おめでとう！
Yay! Teetee and... yay! Sora-chan, congratulations on 1 million subscribers!
いや本当にめっちゃ、感慨深いです、わたくし。なんか、そらちゃんとは、めっちゃ長いんですよ、色々 と、ね。
Honestly, I'm deeply moved. Sora-chan and I go back a long, long way, with a lot of things.
ちょうど、いつだったかな。そらちゃんが、うん、30万人いったぐらいの時から、多分30万人いったかなあっていう時ぐらいに、うん、なんか
Just when was it? From around when Sora-chan reached 300,000 subscribers, probably around the time she hit 300,000, um, like...
そらちゃんがちょっと悩み事があるよって言ってて、
Sora-chan said she had something she was worried about,
その時に私もあんまり伸びないかもしれないから、
and at that time, she was like, "Since I might not grow much more,
VTuber続けていけるかなって悩んでた時があったんですよ、そらちゃんは。
can I keep going as a VTuber?" Sora-chan was worrying about that back then.
その時に、なんかそらちゃんは絶対にVTuberのこの界隈を引っ張っていける存在になるし、
At that time, I was like, "Sora-chan is definitely going to be someone who can lead this VTuber scene,
100万人とか絶対超えちゃうような存在だから、私を信じて続けでよって、
and someone who will definitely surpass 1 million followers and things, so trust me and keep going!"
言ったことがあったんですけど、本当に100万人超えてる！
I told her that, and she really has surpassed 1 million!
すごいよ、本当にめちゃめちゃ嬉しいし、あの時いっぱいいっぱい引き止めてよかったなって、
It's amazing, I'm genuinely so happy, and I'm so glad I stopped her back then,
本当に思います。
I truly feel that way.
でもね、まだまだ始まったばかりだよね、そらちゃんはきっと。
But you know, it's still just the beginning, Sora-chan is definitely...
これからもっともっと120万とか30万とか、50万とか、200万とか。
From now on, even more—1.2 million, 1.3 million, 1.5 million, 2 million!
私はいけると信じていますので、末永く、末永くね、
I believe she can do it, so for a long, long time,
私たちのVTuberっていう世界を引っ張る人として走り続けてください。
please keep running as someone who leads our world of VTuberhood.
私はそんなそらちゃんを信じていっぱいついていきますから。
I believe in Sora-chan and will keep following her closely.
いつまでも傍らにおりますゆえ、神様のご加護がついてますよ。
Since I'll always be by your side, you have God's blessing with you.
本当にそらちゃん、おめでとう！
Seriously, Sora-chan, congratulations!
私にとってそらちゃんは大事な大事なお友達で。
To me, Sora-chan is such a precious, precious friend.
これからもいっぱい、ニコニコ幸せに笑っててね！
Please keep smiling happily with a big grin from now on too!
以上、天神ことねでした！
That's all from Kotone Tenjin!
アイラブユー！ちゅちゅちゅちゅちゅちゅ、かわいい。
I love you! So cute.
はい、というわけで、なんかここちょっと涙出てきちゃった。
Yeah, so... somehow tears started coming out a bit here.
ちょっとユニエイトじゃないんだけど、なんか涙出てきちゃったね。
It's not really unieight, but somehow tears just started welling up.
いやマジで、ことねちゃ、全然違うわ。
Seriously, Kotone-chan, that's totally different.
泣いてない泣いてない。
I'm not crying, I'm not crying.
まあね、ここ3人はね、ことねちゃんのことはすごくよく知っているからね。
Well, you see, these three know Kotone-chan really well, after all.
いやなんか、こんななんか真面目なメッセージが来てると思ってなかったので。
I didn't think such a serious message would come in, so...
ちょっと動揺はしてるんですけど。
I'm a little shaken up by it.
いやすごいなんかそのね、悩みを相談してて、そっからこう行き付けられたってふたりの関係とね、あったんだね、そんなことが。
It's amazing how you consulted about your worries and were encouraged from there—such a relationship between the two of you existed.
あったね、やっぱり最初の頃とかはやっぱりね、どうしてもやっぱりちょっとずつでも、みんな飲むだけど伸びてってて、もうこれがいつまで続くのかとか分かんないし、
That's right, especially in the early days, no matter what, even little by little, everyone keeps growing, and you wonder how long this can possibly last,
この3年目に入ってくるとなんか継続になっちゃってるから、新しいことをなんだろうみたいなもう思い、
and when entering the 3rd year, it becomes about continuation, so you start thinking about trying new things...
時期だったから、ちょっとね、そういう意味ではね、いろいろ悩んだ時期、悩みの時期だったかなとは思いますね。ちょうどこの時期にやめるかやめないかみたいな考えも、
So in that sense, I think it was a time of various worries, a period of hesitation. Right around this time, thoughts like "should I quit or not?"
ちょうどあった時期でもあったから、そういう意味ではすごく、いやあ、よかったよね、続けててくれて本当に。いや本当に、天井よく食べた、よく食べたよ。
also happened to exist, so in that sense, it's really—ah, I'm so glad you kept going. Seriously, Tenjin ate well, ate well.
天井よく食べたね、安心してるとは思うけど、うんうんうんうん。
Tenjin ate well, you know. I think you're relieved, yeah.
それでは4年目いってみましょう！こちらです！
Now let's move on to the 4th year! Here it is!
はい。お、いっぱいあるね、色々。
Yes. Oh, there are lots of things.
うんうんうん、そうよね、この年は。まず1つ目がこちらです。
Yeah, yeah, that's right, this year. First, the first one is right here.
ここでね、まあ、あおいちゃんもね、いろいろね、お化粧勉強して、たくさんね、一緒にこうお化粧を進化していくというか。
Here, well, Aoi-chan also studied makeup and evolved her makeup together with others.
そうだよね、そう。で、私たちはね、どんどん成長する物ですからね、勉強しましたよ。
That's right. And since we grow more and more, we studied hard.
勉強しましたよ。で、私がね、ちょっとね、あの勉強してね、お化粧進化しすぎてね、普段のメイクがね、やばすぎ るっていう。勉強したけどね、普段用のね、お化粧をしてきているからね、勉強お疲れ様でしたね、ということで。
We studied. And because I studied a bit and evolved my makeup too much, my everyday makeup is way too crazy. I studied, but since I did everyday makeup, good job studying, is what it is.
そして次のところがこちらです！はい。
And the next point is right here! Yes.
おお、ここで50万人突破していると。すごい！
Oh, surpassing 500,000 subscribers here. Amazing!
すごいね、早いね。いやあ、びっくりした。私もしこれね、あのさっき見せてもらって、やっと気づいたんですよ、あ、ここで50万なんだって。
That's fast. Wow, I was surprised. I actually just noticed this earlier when they showed it to me: "Oh, it's 500k here."
早いよね。早いよね。早い！
Fast, right? Fast. Fast!
ああ、びっくり。やっぱりこれは、なんかなんて言うんだろう、いろんなところからグローバルに見に来てくださることが増えたからっていうのもあるし、
Oh, surprising. After all, this is—how should I say it—because more people from all over the world started coming to see her globally,
そういう、そらとものさんたちが、そらちゃんて、こんなにこういうことやってるんだよって、いままでのまとめとかをツイートとかで、知らない人向けに書いてくれてたりとかもしたんだよね。
and those Sora-tomos would write summaries of what Sora-chan has been doing on Twitter for people who didn't know,
だからそういうのもあったと思う。みんなの力で、こう、なんか50万人にしていただけたっていう感じがすごいしますね。
so I think that played a part too. I really feel like everyone's power helped make it 500k.
もっとあれだね、そらともがワールドワイドというか、時のそらが、ときのそらがワールドワイドになった瞬間なんですかね。
Even more, Sora-tomo went worldwide, or rather, the moment Tokino Sora became worldwide, right?
ね、はい。
Yeah.
そして、そんな私の次の
And then, my next...
出来事がこちら！
event is right here!
このときにね、私服初めてお披露目しました。
That was when I first revealed my casual outfit.
めっちゃ好き。
I love it so much!
私服。
Casual clothes!
じゃあ、その映像も、あの、せっかくだから見てもらおうかね。
Shall we take a look at the footage?
どうぞ！
Here you go!
いや、まじ可愛かった。
That's seriously cute!
私服ね。
Casual clothes, huh.
初めての...
It's my first time...
ちらされてるよね。
They're trailing, aren't they?
ちらされてるね。
They're trailing.
どうなんだろうと思ったんだけど。
I was wondering what it would be.
可愛い。
So cute.
まだ足しか映ってない。
It's just my feet showing.
あ、足のが映る。
Footage of my feet.
まじか。
So cute!
まあ、普段はね、髪下ろしてないから。
Well, normally I don't wear my hair down...
ほんとに？
Oh, really?
あ、よかった！
Oh, I'm so glad!
今来ちゃばっかりだったから、なんかデート風の服を...
Since I just got it, it feels like a date.
ねえねえ、見て！今日さ、せっかくのお出かけの日だからさ、
Hey, look! Today, since I'm going out,
ちょっとね、おしゃれしてきちゃったんだよね。
I got all dressed up, you know.
可愛い。
Cute!
どこ行こうかな。
Where should I go?
どこ行こうか。
短スカだね。
Short skirt, huh.
生で見みたかった。
I wanted to see it.
そうだね。ちょっと今もう、こう...
Right? A bit, you know, right now I'm kind of...
見惚れちゃってたもんね。
I got so absorbed in it.
わかるわかる。
Right, right, right.
私服はなんかこういうのがいいな、みんなの前で出すにはっていうのはあったの。
As for casual clothes, I thought it'd be nice to wear something like this in front of everyone.
あった。
There was.
普段私はこういう服が好きだから、
Normally, I really like clothes like this.
だから私もう、あの、私服は、なんか普段の私で出たーいって言って、仕立ててもらったの。
So, I wanted my casual clothes to be as if I'm the usual me,
あー、そっか。
Oh, I see.
デートに出かけさってことじゃん。
So it's like we're going on a date, right?
そう、だね。
That's right.
で、だから、ね。
So, because...
目もコンタクトせずにちゃいろね。
I didn't even make eye contact, I was so shy.
そうそうそうなの。
That's right.
それ私忘れてた。
I completely forgot about that.
そうそうそう。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
青い見ながら、放送見ながら、あー！って言ってたもんね。
I was watching while listening to the audio, going, "Ah!"
限界、限界だった。
It was my limit.
ちょっとさ、コンタクトしてないと思って、そうそうそう。
I thought we weren't making eye contact.
そうそうそうそう。
That's right, that's right.
そんなね、この年はなので、けっこうこういうお化粧とか、衣装頑張った年だったんだよね。
So this year, we worked hard on things like makeup and outfits.
そう、だね。
That's true.
うん、確かに。
Yeah, exactly.
最後はね、ちょっとね、あおちゃんに関わっ...あ、なんだろう。
And finally, this relates a bit to A-chan...
こちらです。
Here it is.
初めてメッセージ動画をいただいて、動画に合わせてパフォーマンスして、ね、半端もやったんですよ。
For the first time, we received a message video and did a performance and handcam synced to the video.
はいはいはい。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
やりました。
We did that.
やっぱりこう、いろいろとあって、みんなで集まるのがちょっとまだ難しいねっていう2021年の時期は
There were various things, and gathering everyone together was still difficult in 2021,
だったのて、メッセージとパフォーマンスの動画を先にいただいて、
so we decided to receive the message and performance videos beforehand,
それをスクリーンに出して、それに合わせてパフォーマンスをするっていう演出を
put them on the screen, and perform along with them.
そうだったね。
We did that, right?
したんだよね。おしゃれなコラボ。
It was stylish.
そうそうだから、後ろのスクリーンに出させてもらってっていう出演の仕方は
So, we got to appear on the screen in the back,
確かになかったもんね、今までは。
and that wasn't really a thing until now, was it?
なかった。
It wasn't.
でも新しくて、私のなかでは、やっぱりいろんなこと一緒に記念配信をしたいっていう気持ちはあるけど、でもその場には
It was fresh, and for me, I really wanted to do a commemorative stream together with everyone on various things,
ちょっとってなったら、やっぱりここでしょうと思って
but when it comes down to it, I always think, "I wish we could be here,"
やったのと、
and that's how we did it.
その時にあおちゃんのメッセージだけめちゃくちゃ気合が入ってて、
At that time, A-chan's message just had so much enthusiasm put into it.
何をしたの？何をしたの？あのメッセージ動画をこってこてに編集して、
What did you do? What did you do? I edited that message video meticulously and...
あの、出させていただいたんですけど。
allowed it to be shown.
そう、すごいそらちゃんが笑ってくれてて。
So Sora-chan was laughing so hard at it.
それがよかった、すごい。
It was great.
物真似したんだっけな。
What was the thing she was mimicking?
で、物真似したのに、
And even though she did a mimicry,
物真似直前でカットされてるっていう。
it got cut right before the mimicry!
あ。
Oh!
全然似てなくて見るに耐えなかったから切りました。
It wasn't like it at all, so I couldn't bear to watch it and cut it.
そうそうそう。
That's right, that's right.
こんな感じで4年目も終わったんですが、
With that, our 4th year is also over,
ここで、ある方からお手紙が来ており...来ております！
but around here, a letter came for us!
誰なんだろ。
Who could it be?
お手紙が、私服を始めね、たくさんの衣装をデザインしてくださってるオルダン先生から！あ、先生！やったー！
That letter is from Oludan-sensei, who designed a lot of outfits for us, starting with casual clothes!
ぜひ読ませていただきたいと思います。
I would love to read it.
そらちゃん、100万人ご登録おめでとうございます！
Sora-chan, congratulations on 1 million subscribers!
はじめてそらちゃんの公式ビジュアルを描き上げたとき、そら高く掲げた手に、どこまでも高く伸びやかに、活躍していく姿を願いにかけました。
When you first unveiled your official visual, I wished from the bottom of my heart that your hands raised high would reach up high and wide, and that you would flourish and succeed.
あの時は果てしなく遠い道のりで、自分にとっても男か子供っぽい夢だったのかもしれませんが、
Back then, it was an endlessly distant journey, and maybe it was just a childish or boyish dream of mine,
伸ばした手の先が今こうやって100万人人に届いて、こんな風に夢が叶うことがあるんだって、噛み締めてます。
but the tips of my outstretched hands have now reached 1 million people like this, making me truly feel that dreams can come true.
一旦ですが、関わる者としてすごく嬉しいです。
Though I am just a bystander, I am so very happy for you.
どうぞこれからも伸びやかに、そしてそらちゃんのペースで歩いていってくださいね。今後のご活躍をお祈りしております！オルダンという形で。
May you continue to flourish, and please walk forward at Sora-chan's own pace—I am praying for your continued success! Oludan.
ありがとうございます。
Thank you so much!
今のね、手紙もすごい泣けちゃうんだよね。
Even the reading of it was so touching.
そらちゃんどうですか？
Sora-chan, how was it?
涙出ています。
I'm tearing up.
オルダン先生は本当にね、全部の衣装を今までね、包んでいただいてて、
Oludan-sensei has really... designed all our outfits up to now,
なんかいろんなね、衣装を仕立てていただいてたり、こんなデザインだよって見せてくださる方なので、本当今の私のなんて言う
and they always show us, "This is what the design is like!" So, seeing the real me...
全部をこうわかってくださってる
You understand everything so well...
の
Ah...
その人好みとかもね、そうですね。
and your preferences too, that's right.
するので。
So...
でもこうやってね、こう言って頂けると
but hearing you say that like this
ますます気合いが入りますね。
makes me even more motivated!
これからも頑張っていきたいと思います。
I'll keep doing my best moving forward.
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much!
素晴らしいです。
That's wonderful.
イェーイ！
Yay!
そしてそして、5年目ここまでですね、
And then, year 5, up to here,
お、行ってみたいと思います。
let's go check it out!
はい！5年目は、こちらね！
Yes! Year 5 is right here!
はい。
Right.
おお！
Oh!
なんかめっちゃ光ってる！
It's shining so much!
色が違うの？1箇所だけ。
The color is different? Just in one spot.
なんでしょう。
I wonder why.
え、ねえ、なんでしょうね。まあ、その前に
Well, hey, I wonder why. Well, before that,
まあ、前にはあんまり、この年はいろんなアーティストさんとのコラボが多かった年ではあって、そうですね。
well, before that, this year had a lot of collaborations with various artists, that's right.
それで、初めてね、この一番上に書いてあるのは、ホラーゲームのお化け役みたいなのやったんですよね。
And for the very first one written at the top, I played something like a ghost role in a horror game, right?
私、ホラーゲーム大好きで、まあ、お化け役でみんなを驚かせたい野望があったので
I love horror games, and since I had the ambition to surprise everyone as a ghost role,
叶えまして。
it came true.
ちょっと変わってますね。変わってます。
That's a bit unusual. It is unusual.
あ、私すごいキービィが好きで。
Ah, I really like the key visual.
そう、めっちゃいい顔してるんだよね。
Yeah, it has such a great expression.
そう、すごい良い顔してるんだよね。
Yeah, it has such a wonderful expression.
わかる、わかる。みんな好きだと思う、あの表情。
I know, I know. Everyone must love that expression.
そしてそして、あの金の場所をめちゃめちゃ光ってるこちらです！
And then, the gold spot shining brightly is right here!
この7月27日に100万人突破いたしました！
On July 27th, we surpassed 1 million subscribers!
おめでとうございます！ありがとうございます！
Congratulations! Thank you!
いやでも、私はゆにちゃんたちもすごいって思ってんの。
But you know, I think Yuni-chan and the others are amazing too.
やっぱり、あの1人でずっとやってきている私には後輩がいっぱいいて
After all, while I've been doing this alone for so long, I have so many juniors,
仲間がいっぱいいてっていう状況だけど
and lots of comrades and so on,
でも、ソロでずっと活躍し続けるってそんな簡単じゃないし、ソロでアーティストとして毎年ライブができるなんてなかなか無いから
but continuing to stay active as a solo artist year after year isn't that easy, and being able to hold live concerts every year as a solo artist is quite rare,
やっぱりそういう意味でやっぱ2人はすごいよって思う。
so in that sense, I think the two of you are truly amazing.
ときそら、友達、やめないでね。
Tokisora, don't stop being my friend, okay?
え、もちろんやめない！大きくなっても
Eh, of course I won't stop! Even if I get bigger,
あの、友達少ないからずっと友達でいてね。
um, I have few friends so please stay my friend forever.
やめないでね。
Don't stop being friends, okay?
もらって。いやいやいや、こちらこそ！これからもよろしくお願いします！
Please. No no no, same here! Looking forward to working with you from now on too!
みんなずっと友達だよ。
Everyone is my friend forever.
そして、じゃあ最後行きますか。
And now, shall we go to the last one?
最後は、こちら！
The last one is right here!
2022年9月7日、5周年のお祝い記念日に、5周年記念アルバムも同時に発売しました！
On September 7, 2022, on our 5th anniversary celebration day, we simultaneously released our 5th anniversary album!
おめでとう！おめでとう！おめでとう！
Congratulations! Congratulations! Congratulations!
なんかこう年間こんなに続けられることってあんまり想像してなかったじゃん。
I hadn't really imagined being able to keep going like this for years.
そうだよね。本当にそうだ。
That's right. Truly.
でもなんか、意外と5年っていけるんだなって思った。
But I thought, surprisingly, 5 years is doable.
そうだね。あっと言う間、あっという間。でもそれだけやっぱ濃かったんだろうね、みんなそれぞれ。
That's right. In the blink of an eye. But it must have been intense for each of us.
じゃあね、早く金ににけるように頑張れば。
Well then, if we work hard to reach gold soon—
ね、本当だよ。
Right, truly.
一緒に頑張ろう、頑張ろう、頑張ろうな！見えてないからさ！
Let's do our best together, do our best, do our best! Because we can't see it!
最初はさ、すごい隠れてて、だからこれからもやっぱりずっと初期から一緒に、
At first, we were so hidden, so from now on too, we hope to stay together from the beginning,
友達として仲良くしてくれてる二人と、もちろんね、前に出た二人もそうだけど
and with the two who have been friendly with me as friends, and of course the two who stepped forward earlier too,
ずっとずっと一緒に活動して、ずっと仲良く友達でいたいから、これからも私と仲良くしてくれますか？
we want to keep being active together, stay good friends forever, so will you continue to be good friends with me?
もちろんんです！こうして共にね。
Of course! Together like this.
ご飯も行こう！ご飯も行こう！
Let's go eat too! Let's go eat too!
またご飯行こう、行こう、行こう！
Let's go eat again, let's go, let's go!
普通にご飯行ったりするからね。そうそうそう。最近行けてないからね。
We usually go eat together. That's right. We haven't been able to go recently.
そう、またゆっくりお話をしよう、しよう。
That's right, let's talk slowly again, let's do that.
というわけで、たくさんおしゃべりもしちゃいましたが、ここで終わりにしましょう！ときのそら年表でした！
And with that, we've chatted a lot, but let's wrap it up here! That was Tokino Sora's chronology!
イェーイ！おめでとう！
Yay! Congratulations!
そしてこのあとはみんなで！おお、いい曲ライブしちゃうぞ！
And after this, everyone together! Oh, we're going to do a great live song!
イェーイ！移動するぞ！アイスるよ！
Yay! Let's move! I love you!
ブラックロックシューター どこへ行ったの？
Black Rock Shooter, where did you go?
聞こえますか
Can you hear me?
ブラックロックシューター
Black Rock Shooter
あとどれだけ叫べばいいのだろう
How much longer must I keep shouting?
何処へ行ったの? 聴こえますか?
Where did you go? Can you hear me?
あとどれだけ叫べばいいのだろう
How much longer must I keep shouting?
あとどれだけ泣けばいいのだろう
How much longer must I keep crying?
もうやめて わたしはもう走れない
No more, I can't run anymore.
いつか夢見た世界が閉じる
The dream world I once saw is shutting down.
真っ暗で明かりもない 崩れかけたこの道で
In this pitch-dark, lightless, crumbling path,
あるはずもない あの時の希望が
I felt like I saw a ray of hope
見えた気がした どうして
that shouldn't be there. Why?
ブラック★ロックシューター 懐かしい記憶
Black Rock Shooter, those nostalgic memories
ただ楽しかったあの頃を
from when everything was just so fun—
ブラック★ロックシューター でも動けないよ
Black Rock Shooter, but I can't move anymore.
闇を駆ける星に願いを
I make a wish upon the star racing through the dark,
もう一度だけ走るから
to be able to run just one more time!
怖くて震える声でつぶやく
I whisper with a scared, trembling voice
わたしの名前を呼んで
and call out my own name.
夜明けを抱く空 境界線までの距離
The dawn-embracing sky, the distance to the borderline—
あともう一歩届かない こらえた涙があふれそうなの
one more step and I still won't reach it. The tears I held back are about to overflow.
今下を向かないで 止まってしまう 未来を生きていたいんだ
Don't look down now, or I'll stop. I want to keep living the future!
わかったの 思い出して
I get it now, I remember,
強く強く信じるの そうよ
believing strongly, strongly. That's right!
ブラック★ロックシューター 優しい匂い
Black Rock Shooter, that gentle scent—
痛いよ 辛いよ 飲み込む言葉
it hurts, it's painful, words I swallow down.
ブラック★ロックシューター 動いてこの足! 世界を超えて
Black Rock Shooter, move, these feet! Transcending the world,
最初からわかっていた ここにいることを
I knew from the very beginning that I was here.
私のなかの 全ての勇気が 火をともして もう逃げないよ
All the courage inside me ignites a flame, and I won't run away anymore!
ブラック★ロックシューター ひとりじゃないよ
Black Rock Shooter, you're not alone.
声を上げて泣いたって構わない
It doesn't matter if you raise your voice and cry.
ブラック★ロックシューター 見ていてくれる
Black Rock Shooter, you're watching over me.
今から始まるの 私の物語
My story begins right now!
忘れそうになったら この歌を歌うの
If I ever start to forget, I'll sing this song again.
はい、というわけで、「ブラック★ロックシューター」を歌わせていただきましたー!
Right, so we just performed 'Black Rock Shooter'!
ありがとう!
Thank you!
ありがとうございましたー!
Thank you very much!
いやみんなでこの曲をどうしても歌いたくって
Yeah, we really wanted to sing this song together,
みんな歌ってくれるかなって思って
wondering if everyone would join in.
え、頼んだんだよね。そしたらみんなが
And when we asked, everyone said...
こんなに綺麗に今日パフォーマンスしてくれて、もう私今幸せでいっぱいです。ね! めっちゃかっこよかったですね!
...they'd perform so wonderfully today, and I'm just filled with happiness right now. Right? It was so cool!
最高だったよ!
It was amazing!
超気持ちよかったね!
It felt so good!
いや違うって
No, that's not it!
それで、
And then—
まだ緊張してる、まだ緊張してない？
Are you still nervous? You're not still nervous?
え、ありがとね
Ah, thank you.
5年経っても緊張してるんだから、もうやめてください
Even after five years I'm still nervous, so please stop!
すももちゃんは一番好きみたい
It seems Sumomo-chan likes it the most.
うわー！それね！
Wow, that's right!
ぜひ二人で歌ってほしいって思って、パートをね分けたんだよね
I wanted the two of you to sing it, so we split the parts.
そうなんだ
Is that right?
クラスメイトにいましたよ
There was someone like that in class.
こういうクラスメイトいましたよ
There was a classmate like this!
みと先輩いましたよ
There was Mito-senpai!
え！あー、ありがと！まじで、なんて、え、いろは先輩んの
Eh! Ah, thank you! Seriously, what, eh, Iroha-senpai's—
色々気配りんな
You're so attentive.
でもさ、まだいろは先輩はちょっと、そんなにね
But you know, Iroha-senpai isn't quite... not that much...
みとちゃん揺れのこと好きになったでしょ、今日
Mito-chan, you grew to like swaying today, didn't you?
ああ、いい匂いっすか？
Ah, does it smell good?
え、これ、これ？
Eh, this, this?
いやいいんじゃないすか、全然
Well, isn't that fine, totally?
いいですね、先輩の目からしても全然、やっぱりね
It's good, even from a senior's perspective, still...
そうそうそうそう
That's right, exactly.
みと先輩、ユレと仲良くなってくれましたよね、もう亀みたいになっちゃった
Mito-senpai, you became friends with Yure, didn't you? You became like a turtle.
上からだったりさ
Or from above...
でも、いろはちゃんのおかげで、なんか本当に一つのギスギスしていない秘的な空間ができて
But thanks to Iroha-chan, a truly non-grudging, mystical space was created...
そうだね、歌うときはね
That's right, when singing...
この後はもうバチバチなんですね
After this, it's going to be intense.
めいっぱいくしめようとしたら
When I tried to close it with all my might...
また振り返る
Looking back again.
思い出を振り返ったりもしたじゃん
We looked back on memories too.
そうですもんね
That's right.
いや多分ね、見てる人もすごい懐かしいみたいなことたくさんあったんじゃない、この
I bet viewers had a lot of nostalgic moments too with this.
そうだよね、もうね、本当にさ、人間に歴史ありだよね
That's right, really, everyone has their history.
だよね
Right.
誰？情緒不安定
Who is that? Emotionally unstable!
今日は、今日はね、今日はね
Today, today, today...
本当に、こんな素敵なチェチェンになったのは、ここで一緒にパフォーマンスをしてくれた大切な仲間のみんな、そして応援してくれてるお空友達の中のみんなのおかげだと思っています。ありがとうございます！
I truly believe that becoming this wonderful... thanks to everyone here, and all my Sora-tomodachi supporting us. Thank you!
そんな素敵なみんなはですね
And everyone here is...
なんと、YouTubeをやっているので、さらに！
What's more, they're doing YouTube, so even more!
VTuberやってるんですよ、すごい！VTuberやってるんですよ！
They're VTubers, amazing! They're VTubers!
そしてさ、ユニたちさ、終わったあとゼロ一個増えてるよ
And you know, Yuni and the others, after it finished, a zero increased!
すごい！
Amazing!
じゃあ、ユリたち、よろしくおねがいします。お願いします。
So Yuni and everyone, please treat us well. Please.
はい、というわけで、このあとは、今度ね出るEPっていう、あの、CDがあるんですけど、その中に入る曲を今回ここで初披露させていただきたいと思います！
Yes, so after this, there's an EP coming out soon, a CD, and we'd like to premiere a song from it right here!
イェーイ！やったー！
Yay! Hooray!
こちらははその曲なので一人では倒せって戦いますけど、本当に初めてのみんなのことを思って作ったバラードなので、ぜひぜひよろしくお願いしますが作った作っていただいたんですけど、ぜひよろしくお願いいたします。
This is that song, so I'll fight defeating it alone, but since it's a ballad made thinking of everyone for the very first time, I'd really appreciate your support.
はい、というわけで今日は本当に見に来てくれて、そして一緒にパフォーマンスをしてくれて、ありがとうございました！
Yes, so thank you so much for coming to see us today and for performing together with us!
一緒に聞いてるね
Listening together.
キセキのような キミと作るメモリー
Like a miracle, memories created with you,
ギュッと握りしめ 願ったよ
I clutched tightly and wished for it.
きっと開花する ワクワクの新芽
Surely blooming, budding with excitement,
この場所が初めての 紡ぐ道標
This place is our very first spun milestone.
ちょっとずつでも 踏み入れてみて
Take steps forward, even just a little at a time,
幸せはすぐ 傍にあるものだから
Because happiness is always right by your side.
怯えないで 夢中になる
Don't be afraid, get lost in your dreams,
その力を… For you
Give that power... For you.
この空に花咲かせてみせるよ
I'll make flowers bloom in this sky,
何よりも強い 生命の息
Stronger than anything, the breath of life.
涙は未来の 味方になるから
Tears will become an ally to the future,
隣で拭ってあげる
So I'll wipe them away right beside you.
小さな幸せが 積もる未来へ
Toward a future where small happiness piles up.
奇跡のような キミと作るメモリー
Memories created with you, like a miracle
ギッと握りしめ 願い願ったよ
I held on tightly and made a wish
きっと思いが実る ワクワクの新芽
Exciting new sprouts where feelings surely bear fruit
この場所が初めての 紡ぐ道標
This place is my very first guiding post to weave
ちょっとずつでも 踏み入れてみて
Take a step in, even if just a little bit
幸せはすぐ 傍にあるものだから
Because happiness is right by your side
怖がらないで 夢中 に なる
Don't be afraid, get lost in a dream
その力を... For you
Give that power... For you
この空に花咲かせてみせるよ
I'll make flowers bloom in this sky
何よりも強い 生命の息
A breath of life stronger than anything else
涙は未来の 味方になるから
Because tears will become allies of the future
隣で拭いてあげる
I'll wipe them away by your side
小さな幸せが積もる未来へ
Toward a future where small happiness piles up
La la... 口ずさむ安らぎは
La la... The humming tranquility
足跡が語る 証の結晶で
Is the crystal of proof spoken by our footprints
次はキミが居るから
Next, because you're here,
希望は無限だね
Hope is infinite, right?
一歩ずつから 始めてみるよ
I'll start taking it one step at a time
一緒に過ごして宝物より尊い
Spending time together is more precious than treasure
夢の続きを 叶えて行こう
Let's make the continuation of our dream come true
伝えぇて行こう... With you
Let's convey it... With you
(I) 散らばった (You) 時のカケラ
(I) Scattered (You) fragments of time
たとえチグハグ だって かき集めれば
Even if mismatched, if we gather them up,
ほら 新しいセカイ 開くはずだから
Look, a new world is bound to open
今日も明日も “ありがとう” 歌っていくよ
Today and tomorrow too, I will sing "Thank you"
はい、というわけで、新曲
Yes, and with that, my new song...
歌わさせていただきましたー！
I got to sing it!
初めてこんな、ドバラードみたいな感じの曲を
This is the first time I've sung such a ballad-like song,
歌ったので、エレメンツガーデンさんのね
provided by Elements Garden today,
今日提供していただいた曲なんですけど、とてもドキドキしました！
so my heart was pounding! Thank you so much!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you!
そして、ここからはね、いろんなお知らせもいろいろ喋っていきたいんですが
And from here on, I'd like to talk about various announcements too, but
見てこの可愛いこのステージを！ぬぬんと、あんきも、そして、分かってたかな、そらざうるすもいたりとか
look at this cute stage! Nunun, Ankimo, and, did you know, Sorasaurus is here too,
あとね、こっちにもソファ、こっちにはピアノ、みたいな感じで
and over here a sofa, and over here a piano, like that,
すごくね、なんか、私らしい感じのデザインをね、していただきました。本当にありがとうございます！
they designed it in such a way that feels so much like me. Thank you truly so much!
今歌った曲のね、詳細を喋っていきたいと思います！
I'd like to talk about the details of the song I just sang!
えー、実はですね、えー、来月2月22日に、えー、EPっていうよ、なんか、シングルとアルバムの間みたいな曲がね、「Beyond」っていうのをリリースいたします！
Um, actually, um, next month on February 22nd, we are releasing a new EP called "Beyond"—kind of between a single and an album!
先行配信してる「ケセラ・ソラ」と、えー、ロジカルジックさんとの、えー、提供曲、さらに半クアドラでのコラボがきっかけで、えー、草野華余子さん、エレメンツガーデンさんとコラボした曲4曲を収録しております。
It includes four songs: "Kessera Sora," which is already out in advance delivery, our collaboration songs with Logical Jick, and further collaborations born from our half-quad collaboration with Kayoko Kusano and Elements Garden.
そしてですね、初回限定版には、去年11月に開催したファーストアニバーサリーライブ、そらと時のミルキーウェイ昼夜2公演のですね、模様完全収録したブルーレイがついております。
And also, the first limited edition includes a Blu-ray fully recording the day and night performances of our 1st Anniversary Live "Sora to Toki no Milky Way" held last November!
それが特典なので、ぜひぜひ、ライブをももう一度見たいなって人は、ぜひぜひ、あの、お手にとってもらえたら嬉しいです！よろしくお願いします！
Since that's a special bonus, if you'd like to watch the live again, I'd be so happy if you could pick it up! Thank you very much!
他にも特典もあるので、詳細は特設サイトをチェックしてね！
There are other bonuses too, so check out the special site for details!
そして続いて、えー、今回の記念グッズがあります！こちらですね、えー、2分後、22時10分販売開始となります！
And next, um, we have our commemorative merchandise! This, um, will go on sale in 2 minutes, at 22:10!
数量限定もあるので、概要欄チェックしてね！
There's a limited quantity too, so check the description box!
えー、早速内容を見ていきましょう！こちらです！
Um, let's go check out the contents right away! Here it is!
1月29日発売開始 100万人記念フルセット
1,000,000 Subscribers Commemorative Full Set
going on sale January 29th.
記念ボイス1種 記念グッズ3種類
It includes 1 voice pack and 3 types of goods.
そしてですね、数量限定ではあるのですが
And though it's limited in quantity,
直筆サイン、メッセージボード、ポストカードを
it will include a hand-signed message board and postcard.
書きたいなと思っておりますので、ぜひぜひよろしくお願いします！
I hope you'll check it out!
詳細を見ていきましょう。こちらです！
Let's take a look at the details. Here it is!
まずは、バブミラーです！
First is the "Babumira" (baby mirror)!
バブミラーはオルダ先生に描いていただきました。
The Babumira was illustrated by Oruda-sensei.
自分の部屋でね初期の印象とかねなんかエーまみちゃんがいたりとかすごく懐かしいものになってるんじゃないでしょうかね。
It's a nostalgic item, giving off early stream or "Aemami-chan" vibes in your room.
そして、家で私はドレスを着てとてもポージングしているのでぜひぜひよろしくお願いします！
I'll be wearing a dress at home and posing with it, so please check it out!
そして次がこちら、あんきもタンブラー！
Next is the "Ankimo Tumbler."
ということで、私もですけどね、あの配信の時とかにお水とか飲むじゃないですか。
As for me, I drink water from things like this during my streams, right?
テレワークの人でもいいですし、会社に持っていくでもいいですし、
You can use it at home, at work, or anywhere else.
あのシンプルで使いやすいものにしたので、ぜひぜひみんなもこれになんかの飲み物とかを入れてなんか使ってもらえたら嬉しいなって思います。
It's simple and easy to use, so I hope everyone will use it for their drinks!
そして次はこちら、マルチケース！
Next is the "Multi-Case."
こちらはですね、メガネケースになっているんですけど、メガネを使わないよっていう人もいるかなと思ったので、
This is designed as a glasses case, but I thought some people might not wear glasses,
えっと、普通に使うとペンケースとしても使えるような普段使いができるものを考えました。
so I designed it for everyday use as a regular pen case too.
えっと、メガネケースとして使ってくれてもいいですし学校とかあと会社に行く人は、え、ぜひペンとかを入れてなんか使っていただけたら嬉しいなって思います。
You can use it as a glasses case, or take it to school or work with your pens inside!
そして次は、こちら！え、そうですね、ボイスというのはシチュエーションボイス「空友とホームパーティ」ということです。
Next is the Situation Voice "Sora Tomoto Home Party."
え、シチュエーションボイスといいますか、え、私めちゃんこ部屋綺麗にしたから、ぜひぜひホームパーティ遊びに来てほしいななんていうようなボイスです。
I cleaned my room super clean, so I hope you'll all come and play at my home party! That kind of voice!
最後にこちら、あと20秒後に始まります100万人記念フルセット特典購入、箔押し複製サイン入りポストカードということで
Lastly, for those who purchase the Full Set within the first 20 seconds (wait, within the preorder period),
数量限定でこちら直筆サインとメッセージ入れさせていただきますので
it comes with a postcard featuring a foil-stamped duplicate signature.
よろしくお願いします。ま、もしあの限定間に合わなかったよって人もうるセットでえ、ですねあの複製の方もありますのでよろしくお願いします。
Quantities are limited for the hand-signed version, but the full set also includes the duplicate signed version.
数量限定の方は直筆で書かせていただきます！よろしくお願いします！
Quantity-limited versions will be hand-signed! Thank you!
そして、最後にファンクラブからお知らせが4つございますのでそちらもぜひ聞いてください。え、1つ目なんとときのそらオフィシャルファンクラブが来週で1周年を迎えます！
And finally, we have 4 announcements from the Fan Club! Tokino Sora's Official Fan Club is turning 1 year old next week!
というわけで、え、私から会員の皆さんにプレゼントを用意しました。
To celebrate, we've prepared a special present for all our members!
それがこちらです！
Here it is!
オリジナルアクリルトロフィーを継続特典として、えですね、ご用意しております。スタンダードプランという、あの、年間会員の方で、ファンクラブを1年以上（366日以上）継続していただけると、え、実はこのプレゼントがいただけ、プレゼントするということで
As a renewal benefit, we are offering an Original Acrylic Trophy for members on the Standard Plan who have been continuously enrolled for 1 year (366 days) or more.
えっと、年間じゃないといけないっていうのと、例えば4月に入った人だったら、えっと5月になったらもらえるみたいな感じですかね。
So you have to be on the annual plan, and if you joined in April, you get it in May, something like that.
あの詳細はもらえるのがその時かわかんないですけど詳細をぜひ、あのファンクラブの方の記事を見ていただけたら嬉しいなと思います。
For details, please check out the Fan Club article!
そしてお知らせ2つ目は、こちらです！ファンクラブ限定バースデーメールというものがあります。
And the second announcement is this! Fan Club Exclusive Birthday Emails!
え、会員さんにお誕生日当日に私からお祝いのメールを送ろうかなと思っております。みんな楽しみにしててね！
On your birthday, I'm planning to send you a birthday email from me! Make sure to look forward to it!
え、受信設定をねオンにしておくと当日にバースデーメールを送らせていただけたらなと思っております。えーま今日とかねえ、のし、2月の7日までの人、2月の7日までの人おめでとう！
If you set your email reception to ON, I'll make sure it gets sent to you on your birthday! Today is Feb 7, so happy birthday to everyone born up to Feb 7!
というわけで、3つ目のおしらせに行きたいと思います！まずはVTRをご覧ください。
With that, let's move on to the third announcement. First, please watch this VTR!
その中でやるソラッポングランプリっていうね 企画があるんですけど それのものです
We have a project called the
Sorappon Grand Prix for this.
ゲストにロボ子 すいちゃん みこち あずきっちのメンバー そしてMCにAちゃんをお迎えして
Welcoming Roboco, Suichan, Mikochi,
and Azukitchi as guests, and A-chan,
私に関するいろんな企画をやるということで しかもね3Dでやりますので ぜひ見ていただけたら嬉しいです
doing various projects related to me in 3D,
so I'd be happy if you check it out.
えーそうですね あのYouTubeでもね 途中までは見れるらしいので そのあとファンクラブまで見て企画が出たら嬉しいなと思います
You can watch up to a point on YouTube,
so check out the fan club too!
最後に4つ目のお知らせです
Lastly, the fourth announcement.
なんと ファンクラブ限定でとある動画を公開しちゃいます それがこちら
Releasing a video exclusively for fans!
That is this!
金沢旅行 2月25日(土)・26日(日) ファンクラブにて公開
[Kanazawa Trip: Released on Fan Club
Feb 25 & 26]
えーAちゃんと行ってきたちょ 金沢旅行の動画です 実はね最近Aちゃんと二人で金沢旅行に行ってきました
It's a Kanazawa trip video with A-chan.
Actually, we went there together recently.
Aちゃんがね部屋に来てくれたりとかね Twitterで上がってたと思うんですけど 気づいた人はいるのかなというわけで この動画をファンクラブの方で2月25日 26日の2日間に分けて限定で公開いたします
Released exclusively on the fan club
over Feb 25-26. Did anyone notice?
そしてさらに3月4日には二人でコメンタリーをしながら動画をみんなで見する生放送もやりたいなと思っております
On March 4th, we want to do a live stream
watching and commenting on it together.
プレゼント企画もあるらしいので どんなプレゼントかな 気になるねということで 詳細はニュースでよろしくお願いします
There's a present project too! I'm curious.
Please check the news for details.
以上ときのそらのオフィシャルファンクラブからのお知らせでした みんなホームページチェックしてね
That was an announcement from the fan club!
Everyone check the homepage!
えー告知もりだくさんだったんですが みんなわかったかな すごい駆け足になっちゃったんですけど
There were a lot of announcements.
Did everyone understand? It was rushed!
えーというわけで今日はね大切な友達が身に来てくれて そして大切な友達がこんな配信で一緒に盛り上げてくれて メッセージもいただけて ソラとものみんなにこんなにたくさん見ていただけて本当に嬉しいです メッセージをくださったメンバーの方も本当にありがとうございました
Dear friends came and helped liven up the stream,
and I'm so happy so many Solatomos watched!
いやーここまでこれたのもみんなの応援があってこそだと思いますので これからもぜひぜひ応援よろしくお願いいたします
Coming this far is thanks to everyone's support.
Please keep supporting us from now on!
これからも一緒に歩いていこうね 100万人を超えても止まねぇぞ
Let's keep walking together from now on!
Even past 1 million, we won't stop!
というわけで今日はこれで終わりにしたいと思います ときのそら100万人記念の奇跡 いっぱい呟いてね トレンドに乗ってたらいいな どきどき
I'll end for today. Tweet a lot about
Tokino Sora's 1M milestone! I hope it trends!
今日はありがとうございました
Thank you very much for today!